A Guide to the Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families, 1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families 1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6138
This collection consists of ca. 470 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library from Miss Fanny Edward of Lynchburg, Virginia, through Miss Nellie Gregory of Lynchburg, Virginia, on January 5, 1960.
Biographical/Historical Information
There is biographical and genealogical data on the Dudley and related families in the collection. Some of this information is noted here. Captain Peter Dudley married Nancy Davis, daughter of Friends William and Mary Davis on January 31, 1814. They had issue: John William Dudley (died October 2, 1878) married Andalusia Fourquerean (died March 14, 1878), removed to Cincinnati, Ohio; Thomas Stephens Dudley, unmarried, died from gunshot wound; Mary Elizabeth Dudley married Thomas W. Johns of Appomattox, Virginia; Fanny Jane Dudley married James F. Payne (died February 3, 1882) on December 2, 1847; Nancy Davis Dudley, died in infancy; Peter Lewis Dudley (died December 3, 1856) married Bettie Saunders; Henry Davis, unmarried, moved to California; Louisa Susan Dudley, died in infancy; Deborah Anne Dudley married Reverend William H. Kinckle on October 17, 1865; Maria Rose Dudley married J. Edward Calhoun; and, Robert Leslie Dudley (died December 6, 1900), unmarried.
Stephen Adams, lawyer, judge, member of the Virginia House of Delegates, and captain in the Confederate States Army, was born in Fulton, New York on Feb. 28, 1829. He attended Albany Academy and graduated from Yale in 1850. He came to Virginia and married Emma Camm Saunders in a ceremony in Old Court Street Methodist Church on April 26, 1854. Their son, William Saunders Adams, studied music in Germany and was a professor at Randolph Macon Women's College and organist of note. He married Grace Dudley Kinckle, daughter of Reverend William H. Kinckle and Deborah Dudley.
Scope and Content Information
There are ca. 470 items, (1814-1910)1957 and n.d., pertaining to various families of Lynchburg, Virginia, including the Adams, Davis, Dudley, and Johns families. There are correspondence, business and legal papers, miscellaneous writings, and bound volumes.
There are letters from Andalusia (Fourquerean) Dudley and Ellen Dudley in Cincinnati, Ohio to their sister-in-law and aunt, Deborah Anne Dudley. On June 29, 1851 she writes while still mourning the loss of a loved one. She complains about having to take care of the house and the children because of the inexperience and absenteeism of their young African-American woman from Lynchburg, Virginia and discusses the children and their antics and Dr. Johnston, an apparent admirer and frequent visitor to their home. On August 8, 1851, she discusses the children and the new "kitchen girl" who is better than the previous girl even though she cannot cook and is good with the children. She also describes the procession celebrated by the firemen through Cincinnati of fifty or more companies, each with a different uniform, several bands of the most delightful music, and the representation of the different states' flags. On March 21st, Andalusia expresses her deep sympathy to Deborah over the death of her husband, William H. Kinckle. There is an undated letter regarding family news, her help "Jane" who is "willing poor thing but is a good deal troubled with a disease called laziness," missing the little ones since they commenced school, and cleaning up the house. There are also letters from Andalusia's daughter, Ellen Dudley, following their move from Lynchburg, Virginia to Cincinnati, Ohio. On May 18, [1851], she writes describing their travel through White Sulphur Springs and Hawk's Nest, West Virginia on their way to Cincinnati; she mentions their reception upon arrival, taking piano lessons and staying in a boarding house until they find a place to live. On May 25, [1851], she writes about her new life in Cincinnati, mentioning shopping, clothes, finding a new place to live, and being visited by a Dr. Johnston who appears to be taken with her mother. On December 19, 1851, she writes that hard lessons and music take up much time, reminisces over times with the family, describes the market houses in the city, and writes of family news including a child sick with inflammation of the lungs.
There are letters, 1849-1857, from Henry Dudley in various places including Cincinnati, Ohio and San Francisco, California. Early letters from Cincinnati discuss family news, Mrs. Stowbridge the landlady and her sisters, Catholics, the ladies of Cincinnati as being "unpretty" (April 11, 1849); no news of a fire in the city (May 4, 1849); business reviving somewhat following the cholera epidemic and the Ladies of Covington holding a fair (June 7, 1849); Deborah's presentiment that she will not live long and her growth, his preference for Virginia women, and various women acquaintances (August 24, 1850). In a letter of January 12, 1851, from St. Louis, Missouri, he discusses life at the boarding house and being taken care of by Mrs. Avery and her two daughters and another boarder, Mose Hillard ("one of those boys you read about"); mentions meeting many from Lynchburg including Dick Scruggs, John Cannon, Bob and Dick Walton, Apperson Fitzgibbons and John William Royall; and, advises brother William and family to take up residence in Covington, Kentucky instead of Cincinnati with its members of the Free Soil party and free African-Americans. There is also an interesting letter dated June 24, 1852 from the Steamer Cherokee discussing his trip from Richmond, Virginia to New York, New York, on the Baltimore after the Steamer Roanoke went aground at City Point. His arrival was "amidst all the noise bustle and confusion of the Whig Convention" and his stay initially at the U. S. Hotel. He describes a tour through Broadway, Fifth Avenue, the Italian Opera, Tripler Hall, Cosetti Garden, and Brooklyn. He writes about a business man, Mr. Watson, who has made a great deal of money with his store and "large factory for making sigars [sic], snuff and fine cut tobacco..." He also describes his short voyage with some 400 passengers of Dutch, Irish, French, Spanish, English, and American and mentions a fire on the ship, seasickness and sea animals.
There are letters, 1852-1857, from Henry Dudley while living in San Francisco, California. On November 30, 1852, he mentions the anticipation when the telegraphic signal is displayed on Telegraph Hill that a mail steamer is in sight, the rainy reason, destructive fires, cost of living, and Miss Catherine Hayes giving a concert at the American Theatre. On April 18, 1853, he writes that they expect to have weekly communications with the states and mentions the current monotonous life in San Francisco, the great robber Joaquin, corresponding with a certain young lady, and his failed attempt at growing a beard. On May 28, 1853, he writes about his change of quarters to the house of Carrington and Jeffrey as "chief cook and bottle washer" and describes his living arrangement. He refers to Robert Leslie Dudley's accomplishments in school, mentions having several chances in a grand raffle of jewelry and encloses three gold quarters. On July 30, 1853, he writes about the Fourth of July celebration during which the military were reviewed by General [John Augustus] Sutter (1803-1880) and then formed a procession, and mentions going to Sacramento on business. On March 15, 1854, he compliments the daguerreotypes of Deborah, Rose, and Robert that he has received from Adams and Company and sends regards to George Lyman. He also discusses the entertainment in San Francisco, writing that there are four theatres, several concert halls, and a quantity of stars including Madame Anna Thillon, Madame Anna Bishop, the Roussell sisters, and the Montplaisir troupe. On July 31, 1854, he mentions their Fourth of July celebration with military firing of cannons and an attempted display of fireworks; the death of Colonel [ ] Irving; the birth of a son to Peter Lewis Dudley; the order of 'Know Nothings' being organized there; the numerous 'Do Nothings'; the fire epidemic over the last two months which affected Marysville, Sacramento and San Francisco; citizens' reactions and actions during and after the fires; and, his thoughts on the prospect of marriage. On December 5, 1854, he writes of the difficulties of Peter Lewis Dudley, trying to locate Sam Preston, and the retirement of Messrs. Carrington and Jeffrey from the storage business. He also discusses the weather and how the rain affects the merchant business and discusses the markets, which are full of vegetables and fruits as well as game such as duck, geese, quail, venison and grizzly bears. On January 23, 1855, he writes that he has found employment with Goodwin and Company, one of the largest wholesale grocery establishments in the area, and discusses the current market business. He also mentions the weather, the civilization of San Francisco, and several acquaintances, Mr. Heath, Captain Fair, and Henry P. Irving. On June 4, 1856, he discusses the corruption in San Francisco, consisting of ballot stuffers, shoulder strikers, and corrupt politicians, the murder of the best men in the community, and the governor's order to bring out the militia. The writing sheet contains two sketches (in life and in death) of James King of William, editor of the San Francisco Evening Bulletin murdered by James P. Casey on May 14, 1856. On August 20, 1856, he writes a brief letter on the inside of a bulletin, The California News Messenger, compiled by Joseph Weed and published by George H. Leland. On July 20, 1857, he acknowledges the sad news of the death of their father, Peter Dudley, and comments on the strength of their mother, Nancy (Davis) Dudley. He mentions that Captain Fair has gone to Yreka, California and that hard times are with them, and claims that he still considers Lynchburg to be his home. One November 3, 1857, he writes about the shipwreck of the Central America, commenting on the gallant conduct of the men who sacrificed their own lives in order to help the women and children to safety. On December 4, 1857, he mentions that the rainy season has commenced, that they are in remarkable easy circumstances in comparison to the East, and the loss of employment throughout the East. He also mentions the news of an altercation between United States troops and the Mormons and the possibility of fighting the 'Utahs'.
Letters, 1851-1854, from Peter Lewis Dudley to his sisters are brotherly in nature, often giving advice and supplying news of the family. On March 30, 1851, he writes from Richmond, describing his trip with William Dudley to Cincinnati, Ohio and then to Louisville, Kentucky and New Orleans, Louisiana on the Steamer Magnolia. He writes at length about attending concerts and operas, including hearing the wonderful songstress Jenny Lind as well as a Prima Dona in the French Opera and [Isidoro] Truffi and [Teresa] Parodi. On August 23, 1852, he comments favorably on social life in Lynchburg and negatively in Cincinnati, Ohio and expounds on the virtues of the "hospitality & civility of a gentleman" while reprimanding his sisters over their lack of courtesy in thanking Mrs. Young and Miss Clara Lyman for their hospitality while in Baltimore, Maryland. He expresses concern that Deborah and Rose will return from Cincinnati with "all sorts of notions about the sin and immorality of slavery" after being subjected to the words of the Free Soil party. He also expresses strong negative opinions about abolitionists, the Free Soil party and Uncle Tom's Cabin which he views as an abolition document causing incitement. On June 28, 1853, he announces his engagement to Miss Bettie Saunders and expresses apprehension over his character and making her happy. On March 31, 1854, he suggests that Deborah and Rose buy something for their spring and summer wardrobe on his account with Dudley and Johnston while in Richmond. An undated letter strongly requests that Deborah and Rose not attend the Club that night and promises an explanation later.
There are letters, 1846-1847, from Robert Leslie Dudley following his arrival in Ohio. On October 18, 1846, he writes from Chillicothe, Ohio, discussing his travel through Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, Wheeling, West Virginia, and Zanesville, Ohio to his current destination. He writes that Chillicothe is the "only respectable community...in Ohio," that he attended the Episcopal Church, and that he is moving on to Cincinnati. On October 8, 1847, he writes from Cincinnati about attending the theatre, concerts, museums and the observatory, mentioning wax figures, paintings and a mechanical apparatus representing the 'infernal regions'. He writes that he has no female acquaintances and that there is too much "Yankeeism" in the women there.
There are later letters, 1861-1864, from Robert Leslie Dudley during the time of the Civil War. On February 8, 1861, he writes from Cincinnati about the hard times and the dull business, especially in the book line. He refers to the Ohio papers and the rumors about Fort Sumter and Charleston, South Carolina; the effects of John Brown's invasion; and, mentions peoples' hopes that Virginia will save the Union and almost wishing that she were for secession. In a letter dated December [February ? ]5, 1864, he writes from Headquarters Hindman's Corps, Dalton, Georgia, under the direction of [Thomas Carmichael] Hindman (1828-1868), about the death of Bettie Saunders' father and being busy int he office because of the system that has been established in regard to furloughing the army. On March 4, 1864, he writes from Headquarters Hood's Corps, Dalton, Georgia, under the direction of [John Bell] Hood (1831-1879), that General [Thomas Carmichael] Hindman sends thanks for the tobacco and that he is awaiting a furlough. He also refers to the skirmish with the Yankees and "Old Joe" [Joseph Eggleston Johnston (1807-1891)], probably referring to the Demonstration on Dalton which ended with a skirmish near Catoosa Station. On August 14, 1864, he writes from Headquarters Bate's Division, Atlanta, Georgia, under the direction of [William Brimage] Bate (1826-1905), about food, Bate being seriously wounded, General J. C. Brent being in command of the division, Hood seeming to provide satisfaction and gaining the confidence of the Kentucky Brigade, and longing to go on a rampage.
Correspondence of Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and Thomas W. Johns often relates to family news. There are two letters, ca. 1860s, from Mary Elizabeth "Lizzie" Johns in Appomattox Court House concerning the location of the Yankees around Lynchburg and Virginia and Mary O. Christian's ill child, Maggie and her son, Davis, being sent to the country for care. A letter, May 18, 1882, from Deborah A. Dudley to Thomas W. Johns, mentions her efforts to have published his poetry honoring a Mr. Rawlings. There is a long letter full of sadness and grief, September 23, 1899, from Thomas W. Johns to Deborah A. Dudley, concerning the last tormented days of his wife, "Lizzie"; the "heavy burden of a lunatic child" such as his daughter Bettie; disputes over the settlement of a family estate; being unable to attend Mr. Underwood's nightly church meetings because of his daughter's care; and, good crops of tobacco, corn and sweet potatoes. There are two undated letters from "Lizzie" concerning a plan for laying off ground for a cemetery for soldiers supported by the Ladies of the Memorial Association; Mr. Day's lecture on love, courtship and marriage; African-American servant "Sallie" leaving to get married; the education of Alice, Fannie, Deane, and Willie; and, a request for good snuff.
There are twelve Civil War letters, 1864-1865, from William G. Luck, a medical practitioner, of Graham's Horse Artillery, Virginia Volunteers, Dearing's Cavalry Brigade near Petersburg, Virginia. On March 20, 1864, he writes from camp near Garysburg, North Carolina, about having to "physic" Graham's Artillery and Dearing's Regiment of Cavalry; their very long march; social activities during a trip to Suffolk and Norfolk, including a visit to Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and Thomas W. Johns; a charge on the Yankees in the Dismal Swamp and the capture of several prisoners; the high opinions of Colonel [James] Dearing (1840- 1865); their order to Suffolk and their fight with the African-Americans; returning to Dismal Swamp with Dearing and killing seventy-five African-Americans; the confiscation of bacon, sugar, and coffee; and, not expecting to marry soon. On June 12, 1864, near Petersburg, he claims that Dearings Cavalry andGraham's Battery saved Petersburg from ashes and mentions Lieutenant [J. C.] Rutherfoord of Dearing's staff. On July 25, 1864, he mentions a visit to lady acquaintances in Petersburg, Captain [J.C.] Rutherfoord being a gallant man, fighting and confiscation of goods around Plymouth and Washington, and wanting to get a furlough to visit the Johns. On July 26, 1864, he mentions a visit with a certain widow, an invitation to dine with Captain Cavendish on [William Henry Fitzhugh] "Fitz" Lee's (1837-1891) staff, and men being shot for desertion. On August 5, 1864, he writes about there being no chance for a furlough and the capture of "smoked Yankees" [African- Americans], who were put in front and forced to face the torrent of bullets; he also mentions his loneliness and the pursuit of female companionship. On August 16, 1864, he mentions his low spirits and his young slave, "Penn," running off after a thrashing for bad conduct. On September 2, 1864, near Petersburg, he writes that the Yankee cavalry broke through the picket lines and nearly got to the camp before they retreated and of their anticipation of a Yankee attack at any time. He also mentions the pursuit of sweethearts and correspondence with a special young lady in Chesterfield County and sends compliments to the Johns family. On December 12, 1864, Luck writes that he has been promoted to full surgeon and that they are in camp at Belfield, twenty miles from Weldon, North Carolina without any comforts. In December 1864, he sends a souvenir from a pine tree where [Ulysses S.] Grant was during his last advance to be added to her curious collections gathered during the war. On January 28, 1865, he requests a pair of white gloves in order to attend the wedding of Captain [J. C.] Rutherfoord. On March 4, 1865, he sends compliments to the whole family, especially the Johns, and describes the wedding. He expects the war to become active again and has faith that [Robert Edward] Lee will not give up Petersburg; he mentions the transfer of Colonel Dearing to command [Thomas Lafayette] Rosser's old brigade near Staunton.
There are letters, 1849-1860, from James F. Payne of Lynchburg to Deborah A. Dudley. In October 1849, he suggests that she not attend a confirmation meeting held by [William H.] Kinckle, discusses opinions on confirmation, church and religion, advises her on a trip to Baltimore and Lynchburg, and mentions the fair and its fine exhibit. In July 1852, he discusses family and social activities, vegetable prices, Friends Warehouse business, the organization of the District Court by judges Taliaferro, Nash, Leigh and Baker, and Kinckle's sermon on the death of Henry Clay. There is a touching letter from E. S. Winslow to Payne concerning the death of Winslow's wife (November 18, 1859). There is also an undated letter discussing Deborah A. Dudley's character and how to complete her fine character, religious thought, and the importance of the family circle.
There are two letters, 1864-1865, from Robinson C. Pierce in camps near Richmond and Chester. On October 3, 1864, he writes of rumors of Union movement through Nelson towards Lynchburg and his advice to people to join armed forces in order to save their homes and mentions orders to go into Buckingham and Appomattox to forage. On January 2, 1865, he writes that he has just returned from six weeks of detached duty in Madison, following a narrow escape by William P. Holland and himself with eight wagons because of a delay in orders to leave.
Letters, 1863-1864, from G. K. Turner, 11th Virginia Regiment, Kinston, North Carolina, are chiefly of a social nature. In January 1864, he describes the packed trains on his trip from Danville which included waiting on a train platform with two sick soldiers and several ladies who were oblivious to the sick men. He also mentions his orders to the Sixth Cavalry, Dr. Houston leaving for Richmond to be promoted to its surgeonry. On February 28, 1864, he writes that Dr. Greenlee is being sent to assist him and he then plans to apply for a furlough as he has not had a day off since being volunteered into the 11th Virginia Regiment. He also writes about the cleanliness of his hospital and the long death list contributed to by "sickly North Carolinians."
There are letters, 1852-1862, to Deborah Ann Dudley from various relatives and friends, concerning family news, social life and the Civil War. A letter of May 11, 1852, discusses life in Black Walnut, Virginia, mentioning the family plantation; her mother having two boarders, a teacher and her scholar; picnic parties; improvements to Black Walnut; and, a local beauty, Mary Eliza Owen. There is a letter, July 26, 1861, from R. M. McKinney, Headquarters 5th Regiment, South Carolina Volunteers, Yorktown, Virginia, discussing life during the war. He writes that his time is taken up by his work signing orders and passes and by drills, parades and guard mounting the rest of the time; he has a preference for surviving the war over posthumous fame; he sent mementoes from Fort Sumter and Fort Caswell and that they dug up shell fragments and the bones of men who died at Yorktown during the [Revolutionary War]; there are about 1150 men in his regiment; there was a violent death of a man in camp and there are many sick men; he rides outside the line every evening with Major Green; there are an abundance of mosquitoes; they will never submit to Lincoln; and, he was in the Alabama troops prior to this command. Letters, November 1861, from a soldier in Centreville, Virginia, mention retreating from Fairfax, a social visit with the attention of several females, and the discomforts of camp life due to rain and wind and lack of food. There is a letter, March 23, 1862, from "Cousin William" at Cavalry Camp near Orange Court House, which mentions retreating from Leesburg to Rapidan River; the destruction of supplies prior to leaving; friends fleeing from Belmont to Richmond; support of the draft; the evacuation of the Army of the Potomac; his regiment still being in the rear; being in command of the Guard with the Army of Leesburg; and, marching most of the time, exposed to all kinds of weather and sleeping on the ground. There is another letter, April 24, 1862, from "Cousin William" at "Bivouac" six miles from Gordonsville, discussing life and activities during the war. He mentions moving around in the vicinity of the Yankees; the lack of comforts; various adventures, including the capture of prisoners and arms and horses; his company and Albemarle troops dashing into Warrenton after the Yankees has taken possession; scouting near the Yankee camp; awaiting more orders; rumors of reinforcing ["Stonewall"] Jackson against [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks (1816-1894); having about ten thousand men in fine condition and ripe for a fight; being under the command of General [Richard Stoddert] Ewell (1817-1872) who is under Jackson; the death of Colonel [R. M.] McKinney who fell gallantly leading his regiment; expecting to lose more friends in this war; anticipating the plans of [George Brinton] McClellan (1826-1885); marriage; hoping that the Ladies of Lynchburg will succeed in their gunboat enterprise; the re- organization of regiments and elections, with Hale, Flood, Whitehead, Radford, Mumford and Pitzer; recruits being mustered into the 13th Virginia Regiment at Gordonsville; and, having no respect for those drafted, feeling that they should have volunteered.